Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
本系列基于并受 希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维教导的启发，
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
旨在探讨两个相互关联领域 之间的进化关系，
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
它们在粗钝与精微层面上 展现了人类的觉知。
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
本系列致力于阐明这种复杂的 互动关系——
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
一方是当代科学对人类神经解剖学 （尤其是自主神经系统）的理解，
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
另一方则是传统瑜伽文献中 所描述的“精微能量系统”。
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最终，本系列试图带领观众 踏上这段探索之旅——
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
透过希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维所传授的冥想， 亲身体验这些内在关联。
Science and Spirituality.
科学与灵性。
The debate goes on.
争论从未停止。
But really, scientists and spiritualists are both seeking the answers
但事实上，科学家和灵性修行者 都在寻求答案，
to the same question just in different ways.
只是方式不同，但问题是相同的。
They both try to find the hidden laws of nature,
他们都试图找出大自然 隐藏的法则，
the higher power that created everything,
那创造万物的更高力量，
and use their discoveries to better the life of others.
并利用他们的发现 来改善他人的生活。
And with this interview series, we have tried to learn more
透过这系列访谈， 我们试图更深入探讨
about the intersection of science and spirituality with our guest,
科学与灵性的交汇之处—— 我们的嘉宾正是绝佳典范，
who is very unique in being both a neurologist and a long-standing
他既是神经学家，
meditation practitioner.
又是长期的冥想练习者。
So what better way than to talk to him
有什么比跟他对话并了解更多信息
and find out more?
更好的方法呢？
I would like to welcome Dr. Ashish Prathan
欢迎阿希什·普拉丹医生
on our program today.
来我们今天的节目。
Welcome, Dr. Ashish.
欢迎你，阿希什医生。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Thanks for having me back, Monika.
莫妮卡，很荣幸再次受邀。
Definitely.
当然。
It's always a pleasure talking to you.
与您对话总是令人愉悦。
Dr. Ashish, today we're talking about the seventh energy center
阿希什医生， 今天我们要探讨第七能量中心，
in the subtle system, and we'd like to know
我们想了解
how it is represented in the human body.
它在人体中的对应表现。
The seventh energy center is the most fascinating,
第七能量中心是最引人入胜的，
obviously the most complex.
显然也是最复杂的。
And it is very much a symbol, an anatomical, physiologic symbol
它本质上是一种象征—— 解剖学、生理学层面的象征，
of what spirituality is really all about,
体现了灵性追求的核心真谛，
relative to the introduction that you just so eloquently made.
与你刚才那精彩的介绍相呼应。
So as we have said from the very beginning
所以正如本系列最初强调的，
of this series, adopting a Cartesian frame of reference,
采用笛卡尔式的参考框架——
where we look at each individual energy center, although convenient,
逐步检视每个能量中心，虽然方便，
is not how the system functions.
但并非系统运作的方式。
We have adopted this modality because that helps us to understand
我们采用这种方式，是为了帮助大家
at a little more granular level.
从更细微的层面去理解。
But the entire system is integrated right from the first energy center,
然而，整个系统从第一能量中心，
right up to the seventh energy center, which is what we're about to try to answer.
到即将讨论的第七能量中心， 始终是完整统合的。
Within that framework, given the fact that all
在此框架下，
the energy centers are integrated, the limbic system,
既然所有能量中心都相互连接，
which is the gross representation of the seventh energy center,
作为第七能量中心实体表征的 “边缘系统 (Limbic System)”，
is the epitome of an integral function.
正是这种整合功能的极致体现。
So what is the limbic system?
那么，什么是边缘系统？
The limbic system is something that governs our actions
边缘系统是主导我们行动与行为的
and our behaviors.
关键机制。
It is, one might say, one of the most primitive forms
可以说，它是人体内
of neurological systems within the body.
最原始的神经系统之一。
So if you think about it, the limbic system sits deep
具体来说，边缘系统 位于我们大脑的深处。
If you think of our brain as a kind of a coconut,
如果将大脑想成一颗椰子，
and if you start going inside the coconut,
当你开始深入椰子的内部，
it is literally the core of it all that comprises the limbic system,
最中央的构造就是边缘系统，
whereas the other layers start developing outwardly.
而其他层次则向外发展。
And if you look at the evolution of how this has come about,
如果你观察它的演化过程，
you find the correspondences of the limbic system
你会发现： 当我们沿着灵长类神经系统向下追溯，
the primate neurological systems
（智人也属于其中）
of which the Homo sapiens is a part, that is us,
在进化阶梯上，越是原始的物种，
you can find there are aspects of the so-called limbic system.
越能发现所谓边缘系统的雏形。
So the limbic system in a way might be referred to as a kind
因此，边缘系统虽然可以被视为
of a primitive brain, but it is anything but primitive.
某种“原始脑”，但它绝不原始。
And the reason is, it comprises multiple organs within the brain
原因在于，它由大脑内多个器官 或多个脑区组成，
To call it an organ is probably a misnomer.
因此称它为单一器官并不准确。
And we will talk about two or three of these,
我们会谈到其中的两三个部分，
but that probably might be the next question.
那可能是下个问题。
But that is what it is.
但它就是这样。
The limbic system is situated deep inside our brain,
边缘系统位于我们大脑深处，
and it corresponds to the seventh energy center,
对应着第七能量中心，
and it serves as a kind of a major integrative aspect
它发挥着关键的整合作用，
of the sensory inputs and the motor responses
并将感官输入信息
that the body provides.
作统合协调。
So you just mentioned different parts of the limbic system.
你刚提到边缘系统的不同部分。
Could you just elaborate a little bit more about that?
你能再详细说明吗？
Sure, happy to.
当然，很乐意。
In the last episode, we spoke about the hypothalamus,
在上一集中，我们谈到了下丘脑，
which is related to the sixth energy center.
它与第六能量中心相关联。
But as we said just a few moments ago
但正如先前所说的，
that the whole thing is integrated.
这些系统是整体运作的。
There are two or three other parts of the limbic system
我想简要介绍 边缘系统的另外两三个
that I would briefly like to touch upon.
重要结构：
The first one would be the amygdala.
第一个是“杏仁核”(amygdala)。
The amygdala, we have two amygdalas so to speak,
我们有左右两个杏仁核，
one in the left brain, another one in the right side of the brain.
分布在大脑两侧。
And these are small almond-shaped structures,
这些杏仁状的小型结构 是边缘系统的要件，
And they relate to our memories and our emotions.
负责处理我们的记忆与情绪。
Say, we see something that induces fear,
例如当我们看到引发恐惧的东西，
or fear as a memory that is engraved in us
或是深植内心的恐惧记忆，
is a function of the amygdala.
都与杏仁核功能相关。
So in people who have a hyperactive amygdala,
那些杏仁核过度活跃的人，
they tend to be more fearful and so on and so forth.
往往更容易感到恐惧。
Post-Traumatic Stress Disorders, PTSDs, numerous studies
关于创伤后压力症 (PTSD)， (又称创伤后应激障碍)
that seem to demonstrate a connection between that kind of a state
大量研究似乎都显示
and an overactive amygdala.
这种状态与过度活跃的杏仁核 存在关联性。
Amygdala is again, a very important part
杏仁核是边缘系统很重要的一部分， 因为它既处理记忆，
it also creates the fear factor, and so on and so forth.
也产生恐惧因素，诸如此类。
The other structure that we would really also
另一个重要结构是“海马体” (hippocampus)。
Hippocampus is what is poetically described as a seahorse-looking structure
这个诗意地称为“海马形状”的构造， 主要掌管记忆功能。
Hippocampus plays a very important role in our spatial memories,
海马体在我们的空间记忆 及我们一生中形成的记忆。
in memories that we form over a lifetime,
扮演非常重要的角色，
but also it relates to our time and place memories,
同时它与时空和定位记忆有关联，
so that's why spatial memory
正因如此， 空间记忆在此扮演着核心角色。
The third structure I would like to talk about is the thalamus.
第三个要讨论的结构是 “丘脑”(thalamus)。
The thalamus, again, we have two thalami,
我们有两个丘脑，
like we have two hippocampi, there are two of each one of these,
就像海马体一样， 这些结构各有一对，
one on either side of the brain, but they all sit together.
分别位于大脑两侧， 但都彼此相邻而并列。
The thalamus you can think of this as a massive relay station.
你可以将丘脑想象成 一个庞大的“信息中继站”。
All these sensory inputs of heat, cold, whatever,
我们身体所感受的感官输入
the sensations that we feel in our body,
不论是热、冷或其他触觉，
they are brought up through the sensory nerves
都会透过感觉神经，
and they then pass through the thalamus.
上传到丘脑。
The thalamus you can say is like a major networking junction
丘脑就像是重要的神经网络中枢。
and from the thalamus, the nerves then are projected out
从丘脑开始，
into other parts of the brain, particularly the cerebral cortex
神经信号会被传导到
or the temporal lobe, so on and so forth.
特别是大脑皮质、颞叶等等。
And then based on that, responses are created
接着根据这些信息， 大脑会产生对应的反应，
and they once again pass through the thalamus.
而这些反应又会再次 通过丘脑传递出去。
So the thalamus acts as
因此，丘脑就像是一个 中继站(relay center)，
of the limbic system.
同时它也是边缘系统的一部分。
And then we spoke about
我们上一集谈到了 下丘脑(hypothalamus)，
just briefly the hypothalamus again is a very important organ,
下丘脑是一个微小却非常重要的器官，
very small, very important function by way of its endocrine functions,
透过其内分泌功能，
the way it controls the entirety of the autonomic nervous system
它全面调控自主神经系统
by secreting and controlling hormones that govern our blood pressure,
透过分泌和控制荷尔蒙，掌管我们的血压、
respiration, digestive system, so on and so forth.
呼吸、消化系统等等。
Let's integrate it all together and the pun is very much intended here.
现在让我们“整合”这些知识， 这里的“双关语”是刻意的。
So through the thalamus, through the hippocampus,
因此，透过丘脑、海马体、
through the amygdala, through the hypothalamus,
杏仁核、下丘脑， 以及边缘系统的
through another part of the limbic system
另一部分，
called the anterior cingulate gyrus, which is also responsible
“前扣带回皮质”—— (anterior cingulate gyrus)
for judgmental behaviors.
它负责判断性行为；
What you can see is that the limbic system essentially governs
你可以看到， 边缘系统基本上掌控着我们的
our vegetative functions.
基础生命机能。
It is responsible for 'the state of being'.
它维系着我们的“存在状态”。
This is not a spiritual description.
这不是灵性的描述。
This is literally a physiologic description.
这完全是生理学描述。
Who we are and how we exist in a second to second,
这定义着我们每分每秒
minute to minute temporal and spatial existence.
在时间和空间中的存在方式——
For example, I am seated in a chair,
例如，我坐在椅子上，
I am looking at a camera, I am processing your words,
我看着摄影机，我正在处理你的话语，
those words mean something to me because they are said
这些话语对我能产生意义，
in the English language and so on and so forth.
因为它们是以英语表达的。
That is where my cortex comes in, the higher functions come in.
这涉及大脑皮层的高级功能。
But all of this I am doing without having to think
但所有这些行为都不需要我思考，
about my heart rate, my respiration, so on and so forth.
去刻意调控心跳、呼吸等。
So my state of being literally at this point in time
我此时此刻的“存在状态”
is a function of the limbic system and that is allowing me
完全是边缘系统的功能，
not to overreact, to underreact, to modulate my responses,
它让我不会反应过度、反应不足， 能调节我的反应，
not be fearful, keep my memories kick into place,
让我不感到恐惧， 让我的记忆各就各位，
and manage millions of processes happening
同时管理数百万个 无意识进行的生理过程。
That in essence is your limbic system.
这就是边缘系统的本质。
Therefore, this system is so critical to our functioning,
因此，这个系统对人类功能至关重要，
it comprises various parts but these all talk to each other
它的不同组合部分都相互沟通，
which is why we said if we just look at them
所以说，如果只单独研究——
as individual components, so here is the thalamus,
这是丘脑、这是下丘脑、
here is the hypothalamus, here is the amygdala,
这是杏仁核、这是前扣带回
here is the anterior cingulate gyrus, that doesn't help us to understand it.
那么我们将难以理解它的运作。
So modern neuroscience, although it still adopts this breaking
现代神经科学， 虽然仍采用这种分解
into its component parts approach,
成组件的方法，
it still requires from a neurological perspective
但仍需要从神经学
but also from a spiritual perspective to understand how the whole thing
以及灵性的角度， 去理解整体是如何
works beautifully in sync to come up with the final result
完美协同运作，以产生最终的结果，
that is us functioning human beings.
就是我们这些正常运作的人类。
This structure of the brain,
这个大脑的结构
how does it align with the interpretations
如何与霎哈嘉的教导相呼应？
So beautiful, that's a great question Monika.
美妙的问题，莫妮卡。
So the teachings of Shri Mataji relate to realization
希里·玛塔吉的教导关乎 个体的“自觉”，
or self-realization to be very precise of an individual,
更精确地说，是“真我觉悟”：
of what that true self is, what is the ultimate reality
认识真实本我、认识个人存在
of one's own existence, one's own being
和本体的终极实相。
and this particular aspect is physiologically possible
在生理层面上，这是可以做到。
and we'll deal with this maybe a little later
我们稍后会谈论。
but how it aligns with the teachings of Shri Mataji
它与霎哈嘉教导的契合点在于：
is that the entirety of our spiritual system
正如我们一再强调的， 我们整个灵性系统
as we have said repeatedly is one integrated function
是一个完整统合的机能，
and it is through this limbic system or at the level of the limbic system
而通过这个边缘系统， 或在它的层面上，
is where it all comes together.
一切得以汇集在一起。
Our actions and our emotions, our behaviors and our responses,
我们的行为与情绪， 我们的举止与反应，
our processing of what is around us, our upbringing, our conditionings,
对环境的感知、成长背景、制约，
our affiliations, social, cultural, so called religious, political,
我们的社会、文化、 所谓的宗教、政治归属，
everything comes together and is processed
都在边缘系统层面上整合处理，
at the limbic system level and of course with the help
当然还有高阶脑区的协同运作，
of the higher centers which is what allows us to do it
我们才得以做到。
but that is where it all comes together vis-a-vis
但这就是一切汇集之处，
the alignment with Shri Mataji's teaching
与希里·玛塔吉的教导相符呼应：
so that we are one integrated holistic being
即我们是一个整合的、整全的存在，
rather than just a mere sum of our components.
而不仅仅是各个部分的总和。
So from the first energy center with its quality of innocence,
从第一能量中心的纯真特质，
the second energy center with its quality
到第二能量中心的纯粹知识特质，
or mariadas or dharma as the expression goes
或梵文所说的“maryadas” 或“dharma”，
in the Sanskrit language from the sense of security
从安全感、爱与慈悲，
and love and compassion to the feeling of collective consciousness
到集体意识的感觉，
to feeling relaxed about yourself and others,
对人对己的轻松自在，
having a forgiving disposition.
到拥有宽恕的性情。
All these energy centers that have those qualities
所有能量中心具备的品质，
are ultimately made possible or manifest
最终之所以能够存在或展现出来
because of the limbic system, because of the amygdala,
是因为边缘系统的作用、
because of the thalamus, because of the hypothalamus,
以及杏仁核、丘脑、下丘脑等结构
because of the other components that we have not touched upon
以及边缘系统中的其他组件
within the limbic system.
的共同作用。
So the limbic system allows us
所以边缘系统 透过这个宏伟的演化过程
through this magnificent evolutionary process
让我们能彰显各个能量中心的特质，
that has brought us to this ultimate step
而这个过程将我们带到最终阶段：
which is a breakthrough in our consciousness
透过“自觉”
through self-realization.
实现意识上的突破。
Does that help?
这样解释清楚吗？
Definitely it's a breakthrough in the consciousness
肯定的。正如你所解释的，
with the way that you have explained
这是意识的突破。
and I think it was a very nice recap of all the previous topics
这是一个非常好的回顾， 总结了你先前探讨过的所有主题，
that you have covered in this series about the different energy centers
尤其是关于不同能量中心的部分。
and for those of you who have missed those episodes
那些错过前几集的观众， 建议你们务必回头观看。
and this being the final episode it just brings me to the next question
既然这是最后一集， 我自然想接着提出下一个问题，
about something that you just mentioned towards the end
关于你在上一段回答的尾声
of your previous response about the consciousness.
所提到的“意识”问题。
What is human consciousness and can it be influenced
什么是人类意识？ 它能受内在或外在方式的影响吗？
to collective consciousness?
它与集体意识有何关联？
So that's a very profound question,
这是一个非常深刻的问题，
so thanks for asking first of all.
首先感谢你的提问。
Second I would like to state very very clearly
其次，我必须强调，在探讨此议题时， 需要保持高度谦卑的态度。
Not that the previous things do not require humility
并非先前的事物不需要谦卑， 但这个意识的议题更需要。
and the reason is that we still do not know from a neurology perspective
因为从神经学角度，
although an enormous amount of effort has been expended on it.
尽管投入了大量研究， 我们仍然无法完全理解意识。
Consciousness remains the final frontier
意识仍然是最后的疆界，
and what is consciousness as a function of neural correlates
意识的本质是什么？我们可透过 神经相关物来理解：
In other words if an individual is subjected to an imaging modality
当一个人接受某种成像技术，
such as positron emission tomography or PET scanning
例如正电子断层扫描(PET 扫描)，
and you see what parts of the brain are activated
我们就可以观察到，在他经历
as individuals are put through various different emotions
不同情绪状态时， 大脑中哪些区域被激活。
is one way to understand consciousness.
这就是理解意识的一种方式。
Consciousness implies two things.
意识包含两个层面： “内在意识”与“外在意识”。
So there is a duality there.
这当中存在一种二元性。
What do we mean by internal consciousness?
什么是内在意识？
Internal consciousness is about who I am, what I am feeling,
内在意识关乎—— 我是谁、我在感受什么、
where I am and my position in the universe around me.
我身在何处， 以及我在宇宙中的定位。
External consciousness is everything that is external to me.
外在意识则涉及 一切于我之外的事物。
So there is a clear dividing line
所以“自我”与“非我”的范畴
that I know or I perceive or I am aware of
存在着明确的分界线，
whichever word applies to what is self and what is non-self.
无论你用什么辨识的词—— 我知道、我感知、我察觉到。
What is within me that relates to me and something that does not relate to me.
在我之内的东西，就与我相关。
It affects me but is not me like for example this camera is not me
与我不相关的东西，虽然能影响我， 却不是我。
but it is affecting me because it is recording me.
例如这部摄影机不是我， 但它却影响了我，因为它正在拍摄我。
Something like that.
类似这样。
So consciousness deals with these two compartments
所以意识涉及这两个面向—— 内在与外在，
and how we begin to process that information
而我们如何开始处理这些信息，
is a major part of the study in neurosciences.
正是神经科学研究的一个主要部分。
So that is one part. The external and what is me
这是意识的一个层面： 外在世界与“我”的本体。
If I look at myself in my image in a mirror
当我看著镜中的自己，
I am beginning to look at myself. I know what I look like
我开始观察自己。 我知道自己长什么样子，
because from my childhood I have been looking at myself
因为从童年起，我就一直在看着自己，
and being aware of who I am, and that awareness is a very important part
并且意识到我是谁。 而这种觉知(awareness)正是 我意识(consciousness)中重要的部分。
of my consciousness.
并且意识到我是谁。 而这种觉知(awareness)正是 我意识(consciousness)中重要的部分。
One of the challenges in the study of neurosciences
神经科学研究面临的挑战在于：
is that we are studying the organ with the help of the same organ.
我们正在用同一个器官 来研究这个器官本身。
For example, if you are designing a laptop
就像你在设计一台笔记本电脑时，
you are not designing a laptop with the help of another laptop
你不是用另一台笔记本电脑来设计，
you are designing a laptop with the help of your brain.
你是用你的大脑来设计。
Unfortunately with us what is when you study the brain
不幸的是，当我们研究大脑时，
you are studying the organ with the help of the same organ.
我们是用同一个器官 来研究这个器官。
So we are studying the brain with the help of the human brain
所以我们是用人脑来研究大脑，
because everything is human brain at the end of the day.
因为归根究底，一切认知都来自人脑。
So likewise if I am seeing myself my eyes are perceiving a reflection
同样地，如果我看到镜中的自己， 我的眼睛感知到那是我的反射，
that is me but I am using my eyes to see me.
但我是用我的眼睛看我。
If there is some other way to see me that is if I can remove myself
如果有其他方式能看到我， 如果能跳脱自身视角，
from myself then I will get a better picture of who I am.
我将能更清楚地看见 “我是谁”的全貌。
That is just kind of a basically a logical extension
这只是一种基本逻辑延伸，
and this is where people like René Descartes,
像法国哲学家勒奈·笛卡尔这样的人，
the French philosopher struggled with
他们所挣扎的正是这个难题。
and he came up with this expression because he thought about this so much.
笛卡尔深入思考后，提出了这个说法：
Cogito, ergo sum which is I think therefore I am
“我思故我在”(Cogito, ergo sum)，
and it forms the entire basis of the notion
它奠定了意识二元论的基础。
That is what consciousness essentially is.
这就是意识的本质。
There are multiple states of consciousness
意识有许多不同的状态——
you know you are aware of, then sometimes you are asleep
你知道你有觉知（清醒状态）； 有时你在睡着，
and you are working.
有时你在工作。
There is a lot of research now being done on
目前许多研究聚焦于 我们所知的
what we are aware of as the default mode network.
“预设模式网络 (Default Mode Network)”。
It is a lot that mindfulness deals with.
这也是正念所关注的问题。
What is the default mode network?
什么是预设模式网络？
It is basically the resting state.
它基本上是休息状态。
If you are just sitting, walking, not doing anything consciously
当你只是坐着、走着， 没有进行特定的意识活动时，
as we call it, that is your default mode network.
那你就处于预设模式网络。
You might say it is kind of the background of something
它就像是你大脑的背景状态。
As soon as you start changing your conscious effort from that
一旦你从这种状态转变为 某种专注的、集中的行动——
you are writing something, writing an email, performing a task,
例如写信、写电邮、进行某项任务、
thinking about something in very specific terms.
或清楚地思考某件事情——
So that shifts your focus from the default mode network
那么你的大脑活动 就从预设模式网络
to a more conscious effort.
转移到更有意识的努力上。
That is a shift in consciousness.
那就是意识的转变。
So consciousness is again a function
所以意识是一种功能，
that is both neurological or physiological
既是神经层面 又是生理层面，
but probably is something much more than that.
但可能远不止于此。
We are just aware of who we are as part of a society,
我们知道自己是谁， 作为社会与文明的一部分。
part of a civilization. I come from an Indian background.
例如，我来自印度文化背景，
I am a civilizationally aware of where I come from.
我对自己所来自的文明有认知。
That is also a part of consciousness although that isn't me per se
那也是意识的一部分， 尽管那本身不是我，
but it is a part of who my collective memories are.
但它是我“集体记忆”的一部分。
So it is a long complex sort of a topic,
所以这是一个复杂难解的话题，
not easily answerable but that is what consciousness is about.
不容易回答，但这就是意识的本质。
As far as the neural correlates of consciousness are concerned
至于意识的神经关联物，
we might say that study is ongoing.
这方面的研究仍在持续进行。
There are parts of our brain that become active
当我们从预设模式网络
when we switch from what we said before default mode network
切换到一-个活跃的网络， 再切换回来，
to an active network and then back again.
大脑中会有特定区域被激活。
So that is also consciousness but is there one holistic
所以那也是意识的表现。
simple definition from a neurological point of view of consciousness?
从神经学角度来说， 是否有一个简单、完整的意识定义？
It certainly doesn't exist for now but probably we could say
目前为止，并不存在。 但我们或许可以说，
consciousness is something that is the ultimate outcome
意识是最终的产物，
of the entirety of these 84-85 billion neurons.
是这 840 到 850 亿个神经元 整体的产物。
The synapses within those neurons that major in their trillions,
这些神经元内的突触 高达数万亿，
this entire mathematically impossible to grasp function
这个数学上难以完全解析的 复杂系统
probably produces what we call colloquially as consciousness.
或许就是我们俗称的“意识”之源。
Dr. Ashish along this series,
阿希什医生，在这个系列中，
we have talked about several different parts of the nervous system,
我们谈论了神经系统的不同部分，
about the subtle system.
以及精微系统。
We have also zoomed out to talk about evolutionary meanings
我们也从宏观角度探讨了
to these energy centers but for the purposes of having
这些能量中心的演化意义。
an overarching message for our audiences,
为了帮助观众能有整体性的理解，
what would you like to say as a broad message
您会希望传达怎样的总体信息，
which kind of ties in all the different pieces of information
来串联起这一系列中的 各个信息与观点？
and then maybe at the end you can talk about self-realization
最后，或许您也可以谈谈 “自觉/真我觉悟” (self-realization)
and what is unique about it?
以及它的独特之处？
Thank you. That's again a beautiful question.
谢谢。这又是一个很好的问题。
What I'd like to leave our audiences with
我想留给观众的信息是：
is that neurology, neuroanatomy is still relatively in its infancy.
神经学、神经解剖学 仍处于相对初期的阶段。
Genomics and proteomics are trying to understand the differences
而基因组学与蛋白质组学 正试图帮助我们理解：
and what makes us different as individuals
是什么让我们成为独特的个体，
and also what makes us one as individuals.
以及是什么让我们成为一体。
It's a very well-known factoid that the difference between us
众所周知，我们与亲近的灵长类动物 的基因差异仅约 2%。
So we share about 98% sequence homology.
所以我们有大约98%的序列同源性。
If you look at the DNA molecule with orangutans,
我们与红毛猩猩的基因同源性 高达 97.5–98%。
It's just a 2% variance but that 2% variance
这仅仅是 2% 的差异， 但正是这小小的 2% 差异
potentially produces Einstein's and Shakespeare's
却可能产生爱因斯坦和莎士比亚，
versus also unfortunately the not so wonderful members
同时也诞生了我们物种中 不那么美好的成员，
of her species historically speaking who have brought about
他们在历史上带来了 巨大的毁灭与战争。
But what one tries to say is science is an eternal quest
总结来说， 科学是一个永无止境的探索。
at least for now. We don't have the answers
至少目前是这样。
to who we are, where do we come from,
从科学角度来看，我们仍无法解答： 我们是谁？我们来自哪里？
of spirituality and we'll get to that in a minute.
这些答案或许属灵性领域， 我们稍后会谈到。
But that is what we would like to leave our viewers with
但这正是我想留给观众的一点思考：
at least from my point of view that this is a journey,
这是一段旅程。 科学正在不断前行，
science is on a journey, we are making tremendous strides,
我们取得了巨大进展，
brilliant minds, lot of effort and we are closer to finding
有杰出的人才、大量的努力 投入其中。
the answers to a lot of questions but what is beautiful is to see
我们正步步接近许多问题的答案。 但最令人动容的是
that what spirituality has always been teaching us.
看到灵性一直教导我们的内容。
I would not use the word religion because that can get
我不会使用“宗教”这个词，
kind of contentious but certainly the broad thread
因为那可能会引起争议，
of what we have been told by the so called wise teachings
但肯定是： 那些跨越文明的、由智者们留下的教诲
through different civilizations, there is convergence.
都展现出一条共同的主线，
There is convergence between those teachings
它们彼此趋于一致。
and there is convergence with science and that is beautiful to see.
它们也与科学趋于一致， 这是一件美好的事。
That we are an integrated being, that we are one whole
我们是一个整合的存在， 我们是一个整体，
and that we are a part of a larger reality
我们是更大实相的一部分，
and that reality is also that which sits within us.
而那实相也存在于我们之内。
And again I would bring it back to the limbic system.
再次回到边缘系统。
The limbic system is a great example of how everything
它是一个绝佳的例子，说明了一切如何
comes together and ties together.
交织、整合于一体。
So that is what I would like to leave our viewers with.
这就是我想留给观众的。
Genomics again I would say, proteomics,
基因组学(genomics) 和蛋白质组学(proteomics)——
how the protein metabolome will show us
特别是蛋白质代谢组学(metabolome)，
how this untold number of proteins essentially define who we are
未来将向我们展示： 这数不清的蛋白质如何定义
and what we do.
“我们是谁”以及“我们做什么”。
But then that brings us to the final question
而这一切最终将引导我们 进入本系列中最重要的问题：
What is self-realization?
什么是“自觉”？
So self-realization through Sahaja and through the teachings of Shri Mataji
透过霎哈嘉瑜伽 与希里·玛塔吉的教导，
and through the meditative practice that She has brought forth
以及她授予人类的冥想法，
as a way of humanity to experience allows us at a physiologic level,
“自觉”让人类在生理层面上
I am going to repeat that, at a physiologic level
（我想强调这一点：在生理层面上）
through the tips of the fingers we can feel the existence of a power,
透过指尖，感受一种力量的存在，
of an energy that surrounds us in which
那个能量围绕着我们， 时时浸润着我们，
we are bathed all the time but we are just not aware of it.
只是我们从未觉察它的存在。
So by triggering this inner energy within us which resides
当这股潜伏在骶骨的 内在能量被唤醒时，
in the os sacrum which we dealt with in the first or the second episode,
(我们在第一或第二集有谈过)
its ascent through the so called energy centers within us
它开始上升并穿越 我们体内的能量中心，
also called as chakras and its
最终透过第七能量中心实现突破，
which means its activation of the limbic system
这意味着边缘系统 以某种形式被激活，
in some shape or form we cannot define it
尽管我们当前还无法在生理上定义它。
Just to be very clear as we speak here
需要说明的是：截至2024年12月8日
on the 8th day of December of 2024, maybe in the future we might be
我们还无法解释此过程，
but today we don't know that.
也许未来我们可以做到。
But when that event happens, when that limbic system
然而，当边缘系统被此能量触发时，
is somehow triggered by this energy we can feel this as a form of cool breeze
我们可感觉到它像清凉的微风 从手指尖流淌出。
A physiological phenomenon like this cannot be explained by anything
像这样的生理现象， 至今我们无法用所知的
that we know of neuroanatomy or neurophysiology
神经解剖学、神经生理学， 甚至是药理学来解释。
No drug, no therapy, no state is able to provide
没有任何药物、治疗或意识状态， 能够带来这样的经验。
this kind of an experience and when you get that experience
当你得到那种体验时，
you can feel as a practitioner, I can vouch for this
作为一个长期练习者， 我可以为此作证，
you get that sense of self.
你会感受到那“真我”的存在。
That last but one question that you asked Monika
莫妮卡，您刚才提出的 倒数第二个问题：
which is consciousness. What is consciousness?
什么是意识？
You can feel your true self.
你可以感觉到你的“真我”。
It cannot be described in words.
这是无法用言语来形容的。
I am not going to waste any more time, yours or mine
我不想再浪费你或我的时间 去试图解释它——
trying to explain what that is. It is what it is.
它就是它本身。
There is a beautiful expression in the Sanskrit language,
梵文中有句美丽箴言：Tat Tvam Asi， 意思是“你就是那存在”。
There is no profounder explanation that is required perhaps.
就这样。无需更深奥的解释。
It is a state that you experience and that's a state you experience
那是一种你亲身体验的状态。
for yourself. Books have been written about it,
虽然有人写书描述它，
poetry has been composed about it, paintings have tried to depict it,
作诗歌颂它， 作画试图描绘它，
it doesn't work.
但都没作用。
But it is made very easy and spontaneous by Shri Mataji
然而，希里·玛塔吉让它变得简单而自然，
by allowing us to experience this state within us
让我们能在体内、以及从生理层面 体验此状态。这就是“自觉”。
and that is why we take the opportunity to proclaim
这就是为何我们藉此机会 尽可能宣扬它。
Try to get this because this is not about reading a book
请尝试理解：这不是读一本书、
and forming an idea. This is not about listening
然后形成某种观念； 也不是听某人说话
to someone and forming a concept. This is about experiencing it
然后建立一个想法。 这是你要亲身去体验的，
for your own self through what resides within you.
透过你内在的那个力量。
It is your power, it is your will but it is also your own
这是你的力量，是你的意愿， 但更是你独特的个人经验
individual unique experience which then magically or paradoxically
神奇地或悖论式地
leads you to an elevated state of consciousness.
引导你进入更高的意识状态。
My personal belief and I will end with that Monika
莫妮卡，我个人相信
is self-realization is a physiologically speaking
自觉，从生理上讲，是一种 超边缘系统(supra-limbic)的状态。
supra limbic state. So it is not even at the level
它甚至不在边缘系统的层面上。 为什么？
Because when you are in that state you experience
因为当你在那种状态下，
even for those brief moments or for some hours
即便只是短暂的片刻，或几个小时，
a state where you don't feel thirsty, you don't feel hungry,
你会体验到一种不渴、不饿的状态，
you don't feel the need for the external things that you crave for.
不会渴求任何外在物质的一种状态。
And as a doctor, as a researcher
作为一位医师与研究者，
I have explained it to myself that it can only be because
我只能这样向自己解释：
those impulses that reside within the limbic system
那些存在于边缘系统内的冲动——
that the limbic system tries to control
边缘系统试图控制的冲动
are probably satisfied and are managed.
似乎被满足了，被“管理”了。
Now managing is a big term. There is no physiologic explanation
“管理”这个词涵蓋甚广。 对于那种管理，
for that management. But they somehow seem to be managed.
我们没有任何生理学的解释。 但它们似乎被调和了。
And I have seen this, I have seen this in group settings
我见过这种现象，我在集体场合见过，
where people are sitting for hours together
人们可以坐上好几个小时，
without feeling the need for food
不需要饮水、不需要进食，
or for water or for any other bodily physical comforts
也无需任何其他身体上的舒适，
that one craves. It can only be described probably
这只能被描述为某种
as some kind of a supra limbic state where the needs of the organism
“超越边缘系统的状态”。 在这个状态下，有机体的需求似乎
are somehow innately satisfied and those words are important.
在内在得到了满足。 这些词很重要——
That there is nothing external that is happening.
不是外在有什么发生，
Something is happening within them and that is what Sahaj meditation
而是内在有某些事情正在发生。 这正是霎哈嘉冥想真正的核心。
is truly about. That is what I, at least for myself,
至少对我而言，我相信 这就是“自觉”。
I think there are definitely certain things
我认为确实有些事情是超越心智的。 只要我们接受这一点，
we will always be learning and discovering more and more.
我们就会不断学习与发现更多。
And I do want to say to Dr. Ashish that you have learnt and practiced
阿希什医生，您已经学习和实践了 足够的神经学和静坐。
You have had the intention to share that knowledge
您有意愿分享这些知识 给更广大的观众， 并付出了时间与努力，传递这个信息。
with the wider audiences and you have put in the time
您有意愿分享这些知识 给更广大的观众， 并付出了时间与努力，传递这个信息。
and effort to get this message out.
您有意愿分享这些知识 给更广大的观众， 并付出了时间与努力，传递这个信息。
We have no words to thank you for this contribution
我们无言以谢 您对这个知识体系的贡献，
yet another series with you sometime soon
期待很快能与您再合作一个系列，
but thanks again for your contribution doctor.
再次感谢您的贡献，医生。
Thank you again. Very kind of you.
再次感谢您。您太客气了。
Kind words. Happy to do so. Thank you.
客气话。很乐意这么做。谢谢。
And for our audiences we do want to say
对所有观众我们也想说： 虽然本系列即将结束，
this is not the end of the journey. This is just the beginning of it
但这不是结束，而是起点。
and you can always continue to send in further questions
您可以通过每集的留言区
through comments in each of the episodes
随时提出进一步的问题。 我们将尽最大的努力
whichever way that we can and we want you to stay on
以任何方式回应您。
to follow the guided meditation video by the founder of this meditation
我们也邀请您继续观看 由霎哈嘉静坐的创始人——
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi and do want to thank Her
希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维 引导的冥想视频，
for giving all of this knowledge and giving it for free to people
并感谢她传授这些知识， 免费提供给所有人，
who are now coming out and sharing it with broader humanity.
如今更多人正将它分享给整个人类社会。
Thanks once again to all of you for joining us on this series.
再次感谢大家参与本系列。
Thank you very much.
非常感谢大家。
Shri Mataji: When the Kundalini passes through the five centers
希里·玛塔吉：当灵量(Kundalini) 穿过五个能量中心后，
it enters into the area which we call as limbic area.
它会进入我们称为边缘区域的地方。
This area is all surrounded by thousand nerves
这个区域被一千条神经所包围，
and when these nerves get enlightened they look like flames of VIBGYOR
当这些神经被启蒙时，它们看起来 就像彩虹(VIBGYOR)颜色的火焰，
colors, seven colors and very mildly, beautifully shining
七种颜色，非常柔和、美丽地闪耀着，
emitting peace.
散发着和平。
Now the limbic area is connected to all the areas of the brain
边缘区域与大脑的所有区域相连，
and also to the nerves. So it starts flowing on to the nerves
也与神经相连。所以它开始流向神经，
giving you the new awareness of collective consciousness
并给予你集体意识的新觉知，
called 'samuhik chetana'.
此称为“samuhik chetana”(集体意识)。
Keep your eyes closed.
请闭上眼睛。
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
首先，请将你的右手 放在你的心脏上。
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
左手一直朝向我。
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
现在，在这里你必须在心中真诚地-说： “母亲，我是否是灵？”
Ask the question three times in your heart.
在心中问这个问题三次。
This is a very fundamental question.
这是一个非常根本的问题。
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
现在把右手移到你腹部的左侧，
in the upper part.
在上方的位置。
Here press it.
在这里按住它。
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
这是你的导师中心， 你的指引，你的 Guru Tatva (导师原理)， 如他们所说。
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
请问一个问题， “母亲，我是否是自己的导师？”
This is the question to be asked three times.
这个问题要问三次。
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
现在将你的右手向下移到 腹部的下方。
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
这是完成所有神圣工作的能量中心，
all the pure work is done.
所有纯粹的工作都从这里完成。
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
所以要问六次， 因为这个中心有六片花瓣：
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
“母亲，请赐予我纯粹的知识。”
Six times you just ask.
就这样问六次。
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
由于这样的请求， 昆达里尼(Kundalini)开始被唤醒。
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
现在为了帮助昆达里尼上升， 你必须与祂合作。
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
所以请将你的右手放在左侧，
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
在你腹部的上部， 然后按在胃上。
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
在这里，为了帮助昆达里尼上升，
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
你必须充满信心地-说： “母亲，我是自己的导师。”
This you have to say ten times.
这句话你要说十次。
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
这就是你要说的十诫，
that Mother, I am my own master.
“母亲，我是自己的导师。”
Now, ten times with full confidence.
满怀信心地说十次。
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
现在请将你的右手举到你的心脏。
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
在这里，你必须说， 再次满怀信心地说：
Mother, I am the Spirit.
“母亲，我就是那个灵（真我）。”
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
这是真理，你就是灵（真我）。
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
但你必须充满信心地说： “母亲，我是灵。”
This you have to say twelve times.
这句话你要说十二次。
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
你必须知道 全能的上帝是爱的海洋。
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
但最重要的是，祂是宽恕的海洋。
So He forgives.
所以祂会宽恕。
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
无论你做错什么，祂都会宽恕。
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
所以不要感到内疚， 把你的右手
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
放在左侧，在你脖子和肩膀 形成的角落处
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
现在在这里，你必须 再次满怀信心地说十六次：
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
“母亲，我没有罪疚感。”
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
请说：“母亲，我没有罪疚感。”
Sixteen times.
十六次。
I am not guilty at all.
“我完全没有罪疚感。”
Please say it.
请说这句话。
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
现在将你的手放在你的前额上， 这是一个非常重要的中心。
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
在这里，你必须发自内心地说： “母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Please say it from your heart.
请发自内心地说。
How many times is not the point.
说多少次不是重点。
Mother, I forgive everyone.
“母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
有些人会说， 宽恕是很困难的。
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
但这是一个迷思， 不论我们不宽恕或我们宽恕，
We do not do anything in both the cases.
在这两种情况下， 我们都没有做任何事。
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
但如果我们不宽恕， 我们就落入了错误的掌控中。
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
所以请诚心地说： “母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
现在请把你的手放在后脑勺， 同一个能量中心，在后脑部位，
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
让你的头靠在手上， 然后稍微向后推。
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
在这里，为了让你自己安心， 你必须说，
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
因为你总是感到内疚： “神圣的力量，如果我做错了任何事， ”
please forgive me.
“请宽恕我。”
Please forgive me, from your heart.
发自你的内心去说。
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
现在请将你的手完全伸直， 把你的手掌心
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
放在头顶的囟门骨区域， 那里在你童年时是一块非常软的骨头。
Press it hard.
请用力按压它。
Press hard your scalp.
用力按压你的头皮。
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
现在你要转动它七次， 一边说这句话——这是你必须请求的：
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
“母亲，请赐予我自觉。” 因为我不能强迫你。
So you have to ask for it.
所以你必须请求它。
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
转动七次，用力按压， 并非常用力地转动七次。
Slowly saying that.
慢慢地说这句话。